INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone,
and welcome to the content video
for Graphs--
A Currency Exchange
Rate Arbitrage Example.
OK, so a great example of
graphs used in the real world
are currencies and
foreign exchange.
So maybe you've heard
of forex trading.
That stands for
foreign exchange.
That's where you trade
currencies between themselves.
So you start with
US dollars traded
for euro, traded to another
currency, come back to us
dollars, things like that.
So a specific strategy in forex
is called triangular arbitrage.
That's where you start
in a certain currency
and then move around
to different currencies
and come back to the
original currencies,
and you've made a slight profit.
In fact, here is an example.
Here's a graph of
what I just mentioned.
So triangular arbitrage--
in this example,
it starts with $5 million in
US with a Citibank account.
Then you monitor exchange rates
and realize, hey, I can go to--
I can go to in euro
in Deutsche Bank
and then go to pound
with Crédit Agricole
and then come back to
US through Barclays.
And those exchange
rates will work out.
So when I come back to my
$5 million at Citibank,
I have $5,025,406, given me an
arbitrage profit of $25,000.
That's a triangular arbitrage.
Well, what is that right there?
Look at that data structure.
That's a graph.
To be specific, that's
a directed graph,
where the nodes are currencies.
And the edges are
exchange rates.
So how could you do
this in real life?
Well, you would need
to get those exchange
rates in real time and then have
a way to take those currencies
and move them from one
currency to another.
If you could do
that and then find
the disequilibrium in real
time, you could trade this.
So when all things
are in equilibrium,
if I started with $5
million, it would come back
and be $5 million again.
But when exchange rates
get into disequilibrium,
then there's
arbitrage opportunity.
OK, so how can you do this
in Python using networkx?
All right, so back
to our Python now.
So I'm using networkx here, and
I'm going to do an example using
static data, where I just
put all of the exchange rates
in a 2D array.
So let's take a look here,
so here's my currencies.
I've got the Polish zloty,
the euro, US dollar,
the Russian ruble, the Indian
rupee, and the Mexican peso.
And here's all the
exchange rates.
And I copied these at one point
in time, so they're all static.
They're not updated dynamically.
I'll show you how to do
that in just a second.
So here's all the
exchange rates,
and here's how you read this.
This first list or this first
row in this 2D list is all
of the Polish exchange rates,
the second row, all of the euro,
and so on.
So if I want to
take one Polish--
here's my row for all
my Polish Zoltys--
and turn it into
a euro, I'm going
to get 0.23 euros when
the exchange is done.
If I want to take
my one Polish zloty
and turn it into us
dollars, I get $0.25 US.
If I want to put it into Russian
rubles, I get more rubles.
I get 16.43 rubles.
That's how the exchange--
the exchange rates work.
But that's a perfect graph
data structure right there.
One node is a currency,
goes to another node.
And the edge in between them
represents the exchange rate.
So how do we load
those up into a graph?
Well, we create a graph
object on line 48.
You can see it's a digraph
or a directed graph,
meaning the edges are
directed from one node
to another, in this case,
from one currency to another.
And then we append all these
edges right here, like this.
So check out line 55.
Remember, I'm adding tuples
to this list of edges.
So each of these has
C1 for our currency
1, C2 for our currency 2,
and then our rate from i,
j-- that gives me the
exchange rate from I to j.
And I print a little message.
I'm adding the edge,
I'm using the function
add_weighted_edges_from.
And that function wants
all of them at once.
That's how you create
the graph from scratch,
and I give it all of
my edges to create it.
And then once I've done
that, my graph is built.
All right, so how do
I traverse it now?
We talked about graph traversal
in the past couple of videos.
So I traverse this
graph, but I'm looking
for something specific here.
I'm looking for disequilibrium
or opportunity for arbitrage.
Well, if an exchange rate--
take a look at
these exchange rate.
What do you notice when
they're in equilibrium?
If you multiply
the exchange rate
from the Polish zloty to USD
and USD to the Polish zloty,
if they're in equilibrium,
they should be 1.0.
So let's test that.
0.23 is going from
zloty to US dollar.
And I multiply that times 4.--
what was it again?
4.34, and the answer is 0.9982.
So there's a slight
disequilibrium here.
And again, the reality is,
in real-world exchanges,
there's never perfect,
perfect equilibrium.
So 0.9999 is actually
pretty common.
In fact, 0.9998-- that actually
has some disequilibrium in it.
OK, but my point is, though,
if I take the exchange rate
from one currency to
another and then back
when I multiply them, if
they're in equilibrium,
they should be one.
So when I traverse these here,
take a look what I'm doing,
line 71 here.
I'm using all the
combinations of these nodes--
of these nodes or
of these currencies.
Recall that a combination
gives me all of the sets
but doesn't care
about order, and I
don't either because I'm going
to check the path to and from.
So I don't want
permutation here like I
would if I'm going
to get the data,
I'll show you that in a second.
But because order doesn't
matter, because I just--
I just need a pair in
any order because I'm
going to check the path going to
and the path going from myself.
So there you go.
Now, once I've got that,
I use this really nice,
easy-to-use function called nx.
This is a network
function all_simple_paths.
This gives me a list of all
the paths from one node, n1,
one to another node, n2.
So I'm going to go through all
the combinations of currencies,
all the currency pairs
and check all of the paths
from one currency to another.
Then I'm going to multiply
them, so take a look at lines
81 through 83 here.
I'm going through this
path, and I'm multiplying
all of the edges I see.
Recall from our
previous video, I
can access these edges
dictionary style on my graph.
So g is my graph object.
Path i is the first
node in this edge.
Path i plus 1 is the second one.
And then I use the key
weight to give me the weight.
And then I just go through
and multiply all of them
in that path.
And when I have the path
to and the path from,
if everything's in
equilibrium, it should be 1.0.
So let's take a look here.
OK, let me grab an example here.
Let's go Path To.
Here we go.
Let's do Path.
So I'll just grab one.
From INR to Mexican peso, I
have a path weight of 0.26.
Then going from Mexican peso to
INR, which is an Indian rupee--
it's 3.65.
So let's try this to see, did
we get any disequilibrium here?
So I'm going to copy that.
There's the exchange
rate of that path.
That's not just one edge.
That's the path of
the rupee to peso.
And then I'm going to grab the
path back from peso to rupee.
Oh, hang on.
Mixing up my tabs here.
And it's 0.95, so it
is in disequilibrium.
And then when I go
through and find--
if I go through all of them,
I can figure out, well,
which path is in the
greatest disequilibrium?
And you want it to give you
a number larger than 1.0
because, again, back to
triangular arbitrage,
I want the number
to be greater when
I get back around the cycle.
So the difference between
triangular arbitrage
and what we're doing here
in this Python example--
this has more than
three currencies in it.
This one has, what
was it, seven--
six currencies in it.
But you can have as many
currencies as you want.
So instead of doing
a triangle, we're
doing a full cycle
in a graph, one path
all the way around to another
currency and then all the way
back to look for disequilibrium.
OK, so that's for static data.
How would you do it
for real-time data?
What if you wanted
to do this for real
to see if-- is there
really just equilibrium
in real-time exchange rates?
Well, this example right
here is very similar,
but I don't have static
data in a 2D array.
I actually go and get these
exchange rates from float rates.
So float rates-- let me
go ahead and run this
because it'll give me
the URLs when I run here.
So this example right
here-- let's take a look.
I'm using this URL
float rates, and it's
going through all of them.
I just want to grab one of them.
Let's take a look at this data.
And again, using the Andy
Brim method of processing data
from a web JSON API, put in the
url, hit Enter, stare at it,
figure out the keys you
know, and then write
the code to process it.
So I put in the URL.
I'm going to stare at it,
and I realize, OK, these are
the rates for the Indian rupee.
Here's the US rate.
So check it out right here.
If I want to buy a rupee,
it takes me that much USD,
0.012, right there.
So what I can do
here is I can then
figure out the keys I
need to get these rates.
I need the-- well, if I'm
interested in the Indian rupee
to USD exchange rate, then I
go, I want this URL and then
this key right here, USD, and
then this key rate right here.
So I would go back to my python,
save the USD and the rates.
And I've got those right here.
USD is actually my
second currency.
And then I create
my URL with that--
C1 in that example
would be my rupee.
I go get my JSON
there, and then I
get my rate by my dictionary c2,
which would be USD in my example
and then the rate right there.
So once I've got
my rate, then I can
add my edge c1, c2, and rate.
Now I've got an edge in
that example, rupee to USD.
But I do that for all of them.
And one other-- one other
thing to note here--
In the previous example,
I used combinations
when I wanted to go through all
of the different currency pairs.
But when I specifically
want to go from one currency
to another currency and
the direction matters,
then I want then I
want permutations.
Recall the difference between
permutations and combination.
Permutation order matters.
Like, if you had a
group of 10 people
and you wanted to make a
presidency of three people out
of that, then it
would matter the order
that you pick president and
vice president and second vice
president.
Whereas if you just
said, I have 10 people
and I want to make a committee,
the order of those three people,
would it matter.
Well, when I'm making
a directed graph,
I want the-- the order matters.
I want to know from currency
1 to currency 2, what's
the exchange rate?
That's different than
currency 2 back to currency 1,
what is the exchange rate?
So I use permutations
to get all the currency
pairs where order matters.
They'll get all
the exchange rates,
and then I use my function
add_weighted_edges
to load up my graph.
And you can check out here.
I also created a file
currencies_graph_visual.png.
I save that out
using my matplotlib,
and let's take a look,
currencies_graph_visual.
And there it is, a little
bit messy because it didn't--
the floats are long there.
There's a lot of
precision on the floats.
But if you look at all of the
interest rat-- or excuse me,
the exchange rates from
the different currencies,
they're all correct.
And there's your graph.
Now you can traverse it, look
for equilibrium disequilibrium
and arbitrage opportunity.
OK, and I think that
about covers it.
If you're trying to do this on
your own or for an assignment,
I would say definitely
thoroughly look
through these examples.
Give them a try.
Try them out yourselves.
Try and build a graphs, look at
the graphs, traverse the graphs.
And make sure you're
calculating the equilibrium
and disequilibrium correctly.
And you can see it's a lot of
fun and a real-world example.
All right, that concludes
this content video.
Thanks for watching.